<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-02T17:30:46+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">States of Mind</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">My experience of loneliness in lockdown</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2021/03/05/my-loneliness-in-lockdown.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My experience of loneliness in lockdown" /><published>2021-03-05T09:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-05T09:13:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2021/03/05/my-loneliness-in-lockdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2021/03/05/my-loneliness-in-lockdown.html">&lt;p&gt;As the hours, days and weeks keep moving on during this lockdown period, I have found myself stuck in a state of limbo between ‘bettering’ practices and an internal paralysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A certain pressure loomed over me to take this time of pause as a once in a lifetime opportunity to build up the person I ought to be. Though navigating that person became a maze in which I often found myself lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating space for myself, I returned to my practices in meditation, writing, I focussed on my acting and even found a new love for painting. Going into every day with a sense of hope and a high spirit for the future. Yet something did not feel right. I was still having irrational and irritable outbreaks at my partner, conversations made me exhausted, I was searching but not sure what I was searching for. I could feel a deeply uncomfortable place within me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I didn’t feel good enough, I felt almost invisible at times. I felt alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now? Alone? Really? I live with someone I love who nurtures and creates any spaces necessary for me. A solid community around me. I have my family and friends who I call and catch up with. I have so many means of connection. Feeling alone didn’t make any sense to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious looked at me right in the face. Coronavirus has sent us all into this extreme pause. I am away from everything I thrive on, everything that fills me –  my everyday activeness, my training as an actress, connections to my community, even connections to strangers. Instead, I am faced with myself, someone I haven’t sat with for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I did some googling and found loneliness to be defined as “a gap between the connections that you need and the connections that you have.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Vivek Murthy defines three dimensions of loneliness as: intimate – longing for partner who you share an intimacy with; relational or social – quality friendships, social companionship and support; and thirdly a collective loneliness – a hunger for a network or community of people who share your interests. The lack of relationships in any of these dimensions can make us feel lonely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the intimate, I had the community and relational to reach out to but isolating for such a long period of time has brought me away from the degrees of human connections that I was used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a bizarre and painful feeling but points me towards the reflection of just how much we need others to thrive and how the quality of our relationships must inherit strong foundations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried unpeeling loneliness further and unexpected memories came flooding in of a time when I was the popular girl at school laughing at the lunch table with my big girl group, a time when I would watch hundreds of likes come flooding in on social media, a time when I “had it all going for me”. I was always the pleaser, the performer, the good girl but this was a persona that wasn’t me at my most authentic. I was striving to be someone that wasn’t my core self and it caused a massive emotional tax, meaning I didn’t have a lot to give another person. I haven’t spoken with most of those girls around that table for many years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loneliness isn’t the person sitting alone at a party. It can manifest in so many ways.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it has come with irritability, anger and exhaustion. It flies under the radar, hitting us at a very deep level. It will also manifest when we are out of touch with ourselves, causing true human connection to not be present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Brene Brown’s words really resonated; “The foundation for connecting with other people, is connecting with ourselves, true belonging cannot happen without other people unless you belong to yourself first.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of this comes back to ourselves. The world around us is so often chaotic. We must be able to let the noise settle, centre ourselves and be in a place of peace. So when we approach other people with this sense of rootedness and knowing our worth then we approach other people with a willingness to listen and an ability to be ourselves instead of trying to get something from them which, for me, was usually a sense of validation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now more than ever, it is crucial for us to recognise ourselves and our need for true human connection. COVID, although mighty in its separating force, does have some harmony in it. Our generations have never seen the world come together in unity like this on one particular issue. There’s something in that. No one is alone through all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all at varying degrees of dealing with the pandemic and though connection is undoubtedly important throughout our lives and during this strange time, it’s also important to remember to take plenty of time for ourselves. Let’s be kind, be patient with ourselves and do what we need to do to stay sane.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Community" /><category term="Connection" /><summary type="html">As the hours, days and weeks keep moving on during this lockdown period, I have found myself stuck in a state of limbo between ‘bettering’ practices and an internal paralysis.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How giving young people a voice will make the world a better place</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2021/02/05/how-involving-young-people-in-big-decisions-will-make-the-world-a-better-place.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How giving young people a voice will make the world a better place" /><published>2021-02-05T13:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-05T13:42:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2021/02/05/how-involving-young-people-in-big-decisions-will-make-the-world-a-better-place</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2021/02/05/how-involving-young-people-in-big-decisions-will-make-the-world-a-better-place.html">&lt;p&gt;A well-established dichotomy exists around young people and their involvement in the world. On the one hand we are told that ‘young people are the future’ and that our contributions are essential to society. On the other hand, we are seen as naive and ignorant, unable to handle the world of the adults. To me, it seems the latter view is the better represented: although people aged 30 and under make up 50% of the population we are sorely unrepresented in public spaces, and young adults make up less than 2% of parliamentarians globally. Young people are not included in the decision-making process and in some cases are actively excluded. In a third of all countries, you must be over 25 years of age to  stand for parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of representation not only influences policy but also affects young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In my own experience, I have felt ignored and dismissed due to my age, or that my opinions could only be valid in a ‘youth’ setting, separate to the main arena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a young adult with an interest in issues affecting all adults, my age is often brought up. Often well-intentioned, along the lines of, ‘You are so wise and informed for someone so young’. This reinforces the idea that most young people do not care and that those of us who are informed are the minority. But this is not what I experience. Most young people I come across have strong opinions and values, will happily debate about political issues and wish they were taken seriously. I think the blame is too often placed on the young person and not the system that, generally speaking, does not value our opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at how childhood was seen throughout history can provide some insights into this current outlook. In British society it took until the eighteenth century for childhood to really be valued and even then child labour was commonplace, often starting at the age of 4 or 5. I think it is fair to say that until and around this point, children were valued for their nimble fingers and their ability to look after their aging relatives. The adage ‘children should be seen and not heard’ is still used today by some parents and reinforces the ideas that a child’s opinions and views have no use to an adult. The idea that children inhabit a different world to adults is totally untrue; it is simply their perceptions of the world that differ, but not necessarily because they are ignorant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a power dynamic at play here that is potentially damaging young people’s perceptions of the world and themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If young people feel that their opinions don’t matter to those in charge, they might internalise the belief that it is due to something inherent in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this may also happen if they think that their peers do not value their beliefs, it is heightened by the power imbalance between children and adults, especially those in influential positions. This can lead to young people not wanting to be involved in politics. They may feel excluded and disillusioned and then, potentially, carry these beliefs with them when they become adults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is a wealth of research on how young children see the world and how their perspectives can be valuable.&lt;/strong&gt; Cognitive and language development psychologist Alison Gopnik talks about ‘spotlight consciousness’ in adults, which allows them to narrowly focus on singular things, and ‘lantern consciousness’ in young children, which is expansive and allows them to take information from a variety of sources within their awareness. Gopnik argues that young children are likely to look at all of the possibilities when trying to make sense of the world rather than using their preconceived notions or past experiences to explain them like most adults do. This means that there are certain learning problems that are better solved by children than adults, which Gopnik found to be true. In a study she found that certain problems that required out of the box thinking, were solved better by 4 year olds than adults. Using a similar basis for another experiment Gopnik shows that four year olds are able to change their beliefs because of new evidence, something we know a lot of adults struggle with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Lantern consciousness’ refers to young children’s expansive ability to take information from a variety of sources within their awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gopnik argues that ‘childhood is the species’ way of injecting noise into the system of cultural evolution’ and while she typically works with young children, her research has implications on how we view young people as a whole. A move towards truly valuing childhood and continuing to emphasise the importance of this ‘outside the box’ or ‘creative’ thinking could lead to the emergence of more revolutionary ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alison Gopnik has also written about teenagers and about research done by Eveline Crone of the University of Leiden and colleagues, that shows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Adolescents are more prone to take risks but also more likely to be altruistic — and the two qualities are related’.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research shows that adults can learn from teenagers, that being a teenager is not simply a period of moodiness and rebellion but also one of fostering independence and love. A shift in the way that society views teenagers could help foster altruism. We should be asking for children’s opinions, seeing the value in their new and fresh perspectives even if they challenge our beliefs. The commonly accepted idea that they have less to offer because they have been alive for a relatively short period of time must be put aside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The idea that we must engage children – not only so they feel engaged, but so that our policies work for them – is integral to States of Mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work from the understanding that, to create effective change in how we view young people and their mental health “requires working with children and young people rather than for them, understanding that acquiring responsibility for someone does not mean taking responsibility away from them” (Kirby et al, 2003). This shift towards inclusion is one that is happening in many fields, not simply with children and young people, but also with race, gender and neurodiversity. This approach of ‘working with’ and not ‘for’ represents a shift in the way children are viewed in society and therefore the ways they view their place in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respect is key to this view, in order to move past the hierarchy of power. We know that external actions and views have an effect on the individual’s view of themselves and we have seen negative impacts of this. It is no secret that 18-25 year-old voters tend to be a minority, but for so long this has been blamed on young people themselves rather than considering it as a symptom of a society that does not value their opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By treating young people like they are ignorant, young people may begin to feel ignorant. By respecting young people’s opinions and views, they will begin to respect themselves far more, be more open to sharing what they think and participating in democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is any doubt about the willingness of young people to engage in worldly affairs, I would encourage people to look at the “wealth of evidence” that shows young people “have both the desire and the ability to influence decisions that affect them in their everyday lives. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scie.org.uk/publications/guides/guide11/context.asp&quot;&gt;a survey of 663 young people&lt;/a&gt; (Park et al., 2004) found that the majority of young people thought that they should have, at the very least, ‘quite a bit of a say’ in making decisions about issues that affect them.” In 2020, &lt;a href=&quot;https://circle.tufts.edu/latest-research/poll-young-people-believe-they-can-lead-change-unprecedented-election-cycle&quot;&gt;a CIRCLE poll&lt;/a&gt; of more than 2,000 18-29 year-olds showed that 83% believe that young people have the power to change the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, a plethora of youth organisations exists globally, influencing governments and NGOs across the world. Focusing on issues from &lt;a href=&quot;https://youthfornature.uk/nature-nearby/&quot;&gt;climate change&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://period.org/&quot;&gt;period poverty&lt;/a&gt;, young people are working together to create a more equal society that promotes tolerance and respect. Adults must support us in this fight for a more peaceful, safe world and do so in a way that enables young people to lead the way. We must continue the conversation on how we can make the world a better place by listening, not only to experts, but to young people too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you’re interested in reading more about this topic, jump over to these links:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/climate-change-children-are-carving-out-a-place-in-politics-now-adults-must-listen-and-act-123704&quot;&gt;The Conversation: Children are Carving Out a Place in Politics, Adults Must Listen and Act&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/what-we-dont-understand-about-young-peoples-motivations-129058&quot;&gt;The Conversation: What We Don’t Understand About Young People’s Motivations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalcitizen.org/en/content/2020-youth-activism/&quot;&gt;Global Citizen: 2020 Youth Activism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/change-maker/seizing-the-future-why-empowering-young-people-will-build-a-better-world-b4496b52e607&quot;&gt;Medium: Why Empowering Young People Will Build A Better World&lt;/a&gt;
*&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tbd.community/en/a/youth-untapped-resource&quot;&gt;TBD: Youth – An Untapped Resource&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="youth" /><category term="social action" /><summary type="html">A well-established dichotomy exists around young people and their involvement in the world. On the one hand we are told that ‘young people are the future’ and that our contributions are essential to society. On the other hand, we are seen as naive and ignorant, unable to handle the world of the adults. To me, it seems the latter view is the better represented: although people aged 30 and under make up 50% of the population we are sorely unrepresented in public spaces, and young adults make up less than 2% of parliamentarians globally. Young people are not included in the decision-making process and in some cases are actively excluded. In a third of all countries, you must be over 25 years of age to stand for parliament.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Empowering change from within: why we need to harness the power of therapeutic practices to prepare young people for life.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2021/01/10/empoweringchangefromwithin.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Empowering change from within: why we need to harness the power of therapeutic practices to prepare young people for life." /><published>2021-01-10T17:35:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-10T17:35:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2021/01/10/empoweringchangefromwithin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2021/01/10/empoweringchangefromwithin.html">&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I asked the groups of 17 year olds I was working with what they thought the world would be like if people were more self aware. There were common themes that emerged. People would be kinder to each other, there would be less conflict, people would be more forgiving. Some suggested there would be less cruelty in the world, less war, a healthier planet and integration between communities with ideological differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I listened to them feedback their reflections, I felt such a sense of hope. They recognised with such clarity, the importance of our relationship with ourselves and could visualise a future where psychological health could affect change not just for individuals and societies, but for the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These young people had just started the first module of the States of Mind course, ‘Identity and Self Awareness’. We did a meditation afterwards, where they connected with what was going on in their body, feelings and mind. I do this meditation not only to give them an experience of self awareness but to get a sense of what their relationship to their inner world is like. Some feedback that they feel a sense of calm wash through them, others that they can’t concentrate and get lost in their thoughts. Others feel uncomfortable and have to open their eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tell them that they just experienced self awareness and that their ability to be with the reality of their inner world is one of the most important skills they can develop in life. These young people are 17 and many of them are learning how to pause and reflect calmly on their inner experience for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have learned about the meaning of mental health mainly through social media, often Google, sometimes PowerPoint slides in form time. But rarely have they been given the tools and space to be together and learn how to relate to their inner experience in different ways. They think of mental health as something awkward and surrounded by shame, as so many people do. They have been told that you might have a disorder if you have painful feelings and that it’s a medical issue you talk to doctors about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I aim to teach them is that every experience that they have, no matter how painful, is a part of what it means to be human and that the real suffering comes from hiding the reality of their experience from others and leaving it unexplored. After 6 weeks, they come to see the importance of this, as this young person’s reflection shows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘There is a lot of pain in accepting the past, but it is still a process that I have to commit to. My history is a part of my whole identity, and in order for me to flourish and grow, I must not neglect parts of myself that I don’t want to be shown.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of therapeutic spaces is that they facilitate personal growth. They free us from the judgement we place on our human experiences of emotional pain, help us find meaning and at the same time, expand our awareness of ourselves and others. They help us experience deeper levels of connection, as the more we repress and deny in ourselves, the less discomfort we can tolerate when other people express their pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it says a lot about our society that we have to sit on waiting lists for months to have conversations about our feelings in medical rooms in hospitals. But I understand why. So many of us never had the experience of safe spaces to be honest about what was going on for us. So many of us feared we would disappoint our parents when we admitted our struggle, or feared the harm we would inflict if we expressed our anger. Or worried that we would be seen differently for expressing what we really thought and felt about ourselves. And every time we did, we hid parts of ourselves further away and shut them off from the image that we thought other people would accept. And so it became harder to understand ourselves, to accept ourselves and to bring the reality of our experience to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is possible to equip young people with the psychological skills and tools that they need to transform how they relate to themselves, but it requires time, space and compassionate relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately these resources are often reserved for when young people access the mental health system at a crisis point and even then, they are often offered medications instead of psychological skills and the opportunity to find meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a society, we often view therapeutic practice as something that is reserved for when there is something ‘wrong with us’, when we are alone and don’t feel good. But by integrating these skills into our everyday lives, we can have more of an ability to thrive in the world by living in closer alignment with a sense of who we are and what we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were provided with ways to be with our discomfort, to explore our limiting beliefs, internal fears and understand our coping mechanisms and relationship patterns early in life, we would have an inner navigation system that we could count on when we needed a sense of internal guidance. We could communicate more honestly, understand others more closely and know how to support them when they needed a space to explore their own inner reality. Our bonds between each other would be stronger and we would have more confidence in our ability to make sense of our pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For all human beings, deep social connection is a fundamental need. Relationships &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; therapy as they reflect back to us who we are. As John Macmurray beautifully summarised, ‘We don’t exist without each other.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As these young people intuitively understood, when we feel connected with our true nature and are aware of ourselves, it has significant consequences for how we live our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a society that values productivity, outcomes and external measures of worth, we need to flip the coin. We need to not only acknowledge that psychological health is the foundation of individual flourishing and a healthy society but we need to embed these skills into the systems in which young people develop so that it becomes a part of how they learn about themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investment can bring a lot in return. When we have a healthy sense of who we are and what we are capable of, we are more likely to speak up, to innovate, solve problems and believe we can make a difference to the world around us. We are more likely to ask for help, to collaborate and to grow in the face of life’s obstacles. We are more able to enjoy the everyday and embrace moments of difficulty as opportunities for deeper connection with the people in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our education system is currently unable to provide these opportunities. Students and teachers are buckling under the pressure of the examination system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young people spend the majority of their free time learning from textbooks and do not have enough opportunities to learn about themselves. The focus on academic attainment as the primary indicator of a successful educational outcome causes young people to internalise the idea that their personal wellbeing is less important than the grades that they achieve. Their individual experience becomes lost among the pressure and as one young person told me they feel that they ‘are all alone in this, together.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pressure of achievement in the absence of personal development causes their sense of individual identity to become increasingly split off from the identity that they feel they need  to succeed in life. They feel stressed, without the skills they need to cope, they feel fear, without an awareness of how to overcome their limiting beliefs. They voice distrust in the system, feeling unable to express their true experience to teachers for fear of being judged as incompetent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the education system cannot provide young people with these skills as they develop, we will continue to see an increase in poor mental health both in young people and in adults, as our psychological development at an early age sets the stage for our experience of ourselves throughout our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2021, States of Mind will be launching 2 initiatives to support the education system to bring about change. The first is to launch the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/11/12/online-education-programme.html&quot;&gt;States of Mind education programme&lt;/a&gt; as an online learning platform, making it accessible to schools outside of our pilot area in Newham. The course has been developed over 3 years with 250 students and focuses on cultivating self awareness, self compassion and an understanding of the psychology behind experiences of personal distress. The online resource provides young people in colleges with the opportunity to use therapeutic resources to self reflect and engage in a process of personal development alongside their academic life. The resources can be used by teachers to facilitate sessions that promote their students personal growth while introducing conversations about mental health in a practical, relational and individualised way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second initiative is to design an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/11/18/education-inspection-students.html&quot;&gt;alternative evaluation framework&lt;/a&gt; for the education system, based on the views of students, teachers and parents, to reconsider how schools can better serve the needs of young people.  It is a first step that we hope will provide schools with a framework to understand how a more integrated approach to supporting young people’s academic and personal development can be achieved.  Young people will lead the process, working alongside researchers from the Institute of Education to develop an evidence based and practical set of guidelines, recommendations and practices for schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practice of supporting young people’s mental health cannot be left only to families, the mental health system or teachers, it requires collaboration and for the voices that have been neglected from the conversation to inform the change that they want to see. Our vision for 2021 is for psychologists, students, families and schools to collaborate more closely to create this change together and to use as our guiding principle that the biggest changes in ourselves and in systems always happen from within.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="self awareness" /><summary type="html">A few months ago I asked the groups of 17 year olds I was working with what they thought the world would be like if people were more self aware. There were common themes that emerged. People would be kinder to each other, there would be less conflict, people would be more forgiving. Some suggested there would be less cruelty in the world, less war, a healthier planet and integration between communities with ideological differences.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What would an education inspection look like if students did the inspecting? We’re finding out.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/18/education-inspection-students.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What would an education inspection look like if students did the inspecting? We're finding out." /><published>2020-11-18T09:22:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-18T09:22:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/18/education-inspection-students</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/18/education-inspection-students.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’re excited to announce our new project! States of Mind are supporting young people to design an alternative inspection framework for schools. Here, we share why we are doing this, and how we’ll be going about it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, we have been working alongside young people in educational contexts to develop an understanding of the issues affecting their wellbeing. This has included listening to the views of hundreds of young people across London and exploring their feelings and reflections about their education experiences. Our student-led project, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/09/16/breaking-the-silence.html&quot;&gt;‘Breaking the Silence’&lt;/a&gt;, has evolved and is now a research partnership with the Institute of Education, UCL. Students lead the research and doctorate students support them to capture, interpret and disseminate their findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase one&lt;/strong&gt; resulted in a challenging &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/09/16/students-ofsted-open-letter.html&quot;&gt;letter&lt;/a&gt;, written to the Office for Standards in Education, Children’s Services and Skills (Ofsted), critiquing the incessant focus on high stakes exams that inspections incentivise and offering solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase two&lt;/strong&gt;, led by a different group of young people and presented by Educational Psychology doctorate student, Jaspar Khawaja, incorporated questionnaire and focus group data around the impact of schooling on the shaping of identity and mental health, alongside the extent to which it supports personal development and readiness for life post education. Read more about his findings &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/11/04/the-impact-of-school-on-students-mental-health.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has emerged are a complex set of themes that demonstrate the profound impact of the education system on young peoples’ sense of identity, mental health, wellbeing and preparedness for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Throughout our research, young people have consistently reported feeling de-individualised, stressed and pressured to maintain an identity that does not value their personal strengths or individual needs. They have been telling us that something is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The student innovators working with States of Mind believe that the mental health and wellbeing of young people should be a key indicator of the efficacy of the education system itself. These essential measures are not considered and, by implication, deemed low priority to Ofsted or the Department for Education. Young people have never been asked if they feel Ofsted’s measurements of schooling are valid, or if they perceive their chosen success criteria expedites education that meets their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next phase of our work builds on our earlier work. Phase three will enable a group of students from two London colleges, working throughout the school year, to research the current Ofsted inspection framework, explore its impact on the education provision they receive. Using a Participatory Action Research approach, the aim is to reimagine an education inspection framework that places young people at the centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fascinating questions arise such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘If young people were to evaluate the education that ostensibly supports them, what would they measure and how?’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘What might young people perceive to be appropriate “success criteria” for an education inspection?’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘Given that “what is treasured, is measured”, what values and beliefs will underpin a student-led education inspection?”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our previous work has shown that young people possess profound insights into how the system can be adapted to better meet their needs. This project will draw on young people’s lived experience and empower them to create change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants will formulate research questions and gather data from a range of stakeholders which might include young people, teachers, parents, professionals and Ofsted inspectors. IOE doctorate students, alongside the States of Mind team will support the young people in developing research skills in regards to collating and evaluating their findings. They will work together to formulate the values underpinning a new inspection framework, alongside measurements of success. Later in the academic year, the young people will implement their alternative education inspection framework and reflect upon the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;38 students applied and 12 students have been chosen to lead the project. The project will adopt a dynamic and innovative approach to solving a complex issue that demands alternatives be considered. It brings together students and researchers, two worlds that rarely cooperate in traditional academic study. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/09/28/young-people-education-research.html&quot;&gt;Young people are often viewed as experimental subjects&lt;/a&gt;; here, they are active participants in all aspects of research that directly affects their experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research findings and insights gained from implementing the new framework will be presented at a public event in July, hosted by the IOE. We welcome schools, psychologists and anybody interested in educational reform to attend. To express your interest, &lt;a href=&quot;http://eepurl.com/hiMQMb&quot;&gt;join our mailing list here&lt;/a&gt; for termly updates and news on the project . Stay tuned for announcements about the event and how to register.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking forward to co-developing something new, valuable and inspiring, with the potential to challenge the taken-for-granted values underpinning our education system. We’ll be sharing the journey with you as it unfolds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stay tuned on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/news-and-events&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;, and on our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/statesofmindorg_/&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/statesofmind_20&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="education" /><category term="innovation" /><category term="change" /><summary type="html">We’re excited to announce our new project! States of Mind are supporting young people to design an alternative inspection framework for schools. Here, we share why we are doing this, and how we’ll be going about it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I co-designed and tested States of Mind’s new online mental health course. Here’s what I found…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/12/online-education-programme.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I co-designed and tested States of Mind's new online mental health course. Here's what I found..." /><published>2020-11-12T16:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-12T16:01:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/12/online-education-programme</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/12/online-education-programme.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our education work involves working in London colleges and schools, providing mental health education and supporting young people to address challenges affecting individual and peer wellbeing. With the huge changes our world has experienced this year, we decided it was time to make our mental health education programme accessible to even more young people. So… we’re going online!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using our existing education model as the foundation, we’ve created and piloted our first online course. Uniting knowledge, theory and self reflection, it aims to increase understanding about mental health, ourselves, others, and our world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right now we’re making final changes and plan to launch it fully in early 2021. Here, team member Ella shares what it was like to co-design the course, and then to work through the content as a learner.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am in a very unique position when it comes to discussing this course as I had the privilege of creating it with States of Mind founder Bea, and then completing it as a participant. As co-designer I was already very familiar with the course’s content, yet I learnt so much from working through the content and gained a greater understanding of myself and others around me. I now apply the theories and ideas I have learned in my everyday life, and perhaps most importantly,  the insights I have gained through reflecting on the material in the handbook have greatly influenced how I relate to myself and those around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This course is not only helpful for those struggling with life, who may feel like the mental health system isn’t supporting them enough, but also for anyone, young or old, who is searching for greater understanding of who they are and why they feel or act in the ways they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course comprises five modules: Identity and Self Awareness; Body, Feelings, Mind; Relationships; Anxiety and Depression and Low mood. Each module delves into the chosen topic in detail but also contains information pertinent to all areas of life and the other modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘Identity and Self Awareness’&lt;/strong&gt; is a nice starting point to gaining this greater understanding and it introduces the need to be vulnerable with oneself while completing the course. I personally noticed resistance in myself to some of the handbook exercises and therefore got some practice in compassionately responding to feelings of discomfort. This skill is essential for the course and will be learnt or built up as one progresses. It is a reminder that the moments where we usually respond with frustration or annoyance are usually the ones where kindness is needed the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘Body, Feelings, Mind’&lt;/strong&gt; begins an exploration into how we identify with the different aspects of our being and how this affects how we show up in the world. It contains a truly beautiful meditation that reminds me that ‘I am my body but I am also more than that. I am my mind but I’m also more than that and I am my feelings but I also more than them’. This mantra reminds me of the complexity of our identity and that while these different aspects may seem at odds with one another they coexist beautifully within us. Meditations are a key part of the course and they remind me that while they can feel divisive sometimes, you are either a  “yogi” or you’re not, meditation is a tool that can be accessible to all of us and can help to heighten the connection that we feel with all parts of our person. Working on this connection allows us to remember that we are whole without feeling a need to change or look externally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These first two modules focus on possibly the most important relationship: our relationship with ourselves and this is then developed in the third module: &lt;strong&gt;‘Relationships’&lt;/strong&gt;. It explores the idea that the company we keep has an affect on our well-being and that our primary relationships have long standing impacts on our mental health. It stresses the importance of authenticity in our relationships and the link between how we feel and how authentic we can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self compassion is a key component of all the modules, but especially in ‘Relationships’. The self compassion meditation offers a chance to explore how compassionate we are with ourselves and how by adopting a more compassionate attitude we can support our well-being. It also offers a chance to have a truly transcendental experience, as I discovered. I had been lucky enough to engage with a few of Bea’s meditations while creating the course, and love her style and this guided meditation is up there in my favourites for sure. Every person’s experience is different and even the same person can have radically different experiences with a meditation depending on the context in which they engage with it but for me, while completing the course, I was able to connect with an embodied connectedness that is beyond words; I could almost feel myself unlearning old patterns! It was an odd feeling to be learning so much about myself while on my laptop but it is an experience I am very grateful for. This course provided me with an opportunity to look at the areas of my life that I am unhappy about and look for tangible ways to improve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is so incredibly important that courses like this exist because they give us chances to explore our feelings outside of a formal setting, like therapy, and do so in a way that engages not only our mind, but our soul and body too. There are opportunities to intellectually explore and opportunities to experience and feel, and in life these can feel disconnected. Completing this course reminded me that it is possible to show up using my mind, body and soul and that in the times when I inevitably cannot show up as fully as I wish too, kindness should be my immediate response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While helping to create it, I wanted the course to act as a reminder to young people that we have more power than we realise or are told.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/08/28/nhs-mental-health-young-people.html&quot;&gt;many years&lt;/a&gt; feeling powerless when it came to how I felt, I thought that it was up to professionals to ‘treat’ me and when that did not work I spiralled into thinking that I could never experience life in a peaceful and fulfilling way. I want young people to know that most of the time our suffering is not permanent and that we can take steps to understand why we feel overwhelmed or why we may not feel anything a lot of the time. It took me a long time to detach from the thought that my ‘mental health problems’ were inherent and to instead see the beliefs I held as a result of what I had experienced as a child and teenager and how I had dealt with these experiences. There is no simple ‘cure’ for these feelings and neither is there one method that will work for everyone but, for me, a greater understanding of psychology and theories about mental health allowed me to take more responsibility for how I felt and to become discerning. As a young person, who is the ‘patient’, it can be tricky to express our opinions to mental health specialists. I struggled with the power imbalance between myself and various medical professionals for a long time, staying quiet even if I disagreed with their ideas or assessment of me. Completing this course has given me a greater feeling of confidence when it comes to working with professionals on my mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I no longer feel like I am being ‘treated’ but that it is a two way process of learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a young person I feel a lot of anxiety, both about external and internal affairs. The &lt;strong&gt;‘Anxiety’&lt;/strong&gt; module of the course was therefore very helpful for me and it includes many really useful graphs and pictorial representations to enhance learning. I was able to address some anxiety surrounding the course, especially the handbook, in this module too. At first I rushed to fill up all the space when answering questions and only after taking a step back and asking ‘who am i performing for?’ was I able to recognise that sometimes less is more. Sometimes I wanted to write a paragraph and sometimes one word means much more to me. At the beginning I had not realised that I felt like I was under the same stress from school of needing to write a certain amount, trying to show that I understood the material and was engaged. The module’s focus on anxiety allowed me to tune into my own anxiety, sometimes prompted by the course material and sometimes inspired by its focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The module introduces the concept of limiting beliefs: beliefs that are rooted in fear. This was one of the first ideas that Bea and I explored together and I was very familiar with the notion by the time I came to this section. Surprisingly I was still challenged by these slides, reminding me that my growth never ends but simply changes and evolves. It was an important realisation that this course is not only useful for people who have never engaged with these concepts but also for people who are very familiar with them. Learning about theories and applying them to yourself are two very different experiences and I think it highlights the value that this course has for all no matter your experience. The ideas around changing and evolving are key to this course as it is fundamentally about looking at our beliefs and actions and questioning whether they serve or limit us. This does not mean that we denounce or label them in any way but that we recognise that we have changed and the behaviours that helped the past versions of ourselves cope may not apply to our present life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final module &lt;strong&gt;‘Depression and Low Mood’&lt;/strong&gt; is very intellectually stimulating. It introduces psychosocial theories of depression which will be foreign for many people and can radically alter the way those of us  with depression see ourselves and we see those we know who struggle with it. It introduces the idea that depression is not only an individual struggle but also one that affects all of society and is very much a political issue. Prior to meeting Bea and working with her, I had many experiences with CAMHs which I have elaborated on in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/08/28/nhs-mental-health-young-people.html&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;. In that article I argued that what young people need is a mental health system that values vulnerability, responsibility, truth and compassion and while we may not have that yet this course does embody these values. For me to explore such an emotionally charged topic like depression it was necessary to come from a place of acceptance and love and I felt the course supported me to do this. The calming look of the course, muted pastel colours and a rounded font, really helped here and it reminded me just how important the atmosphere is when talking about sensitive issues. This is another area where CAMHs fall short, the rooms that I have experienced are bare and often uncomfortable to be in. As individuals we cannot wait for CAMHs to transform themselves into the mental health system we so desperately need and so courses like this are key in taking some of the responsibility away from a failing system and placing it on ourselves. This can be a scary feeling and so it is important that individuals are supported while completing the course and is why facilitating sessions alongside individual completion is such a valuable thing and compliments nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This module helps to reinforce in the individual just how widespread depression is, especially in the Western world and how we as individuals must help to turn the tide. It is adversely affected by the shame we as a society seem to feel in talking about experiences of depression and by educating ourselves we can begin to remove the individual shame that we may feel about our own experience or about others’. There is a need for us to reduce inequality to help mental health and this provides a useful reminder that nothing is isolated, mental health work is about improving society as a whole and to advocate effectively that must be taken into account. We must acknowledge that experiences between different groups of people can be fundamentally different and that this must inform the way we approach talking about mental health and the language we use. The course takes this into account, avoiding definite language and keeping in mind that we cannot know someone else’s experience only make educated guesses about it. This is why the handbook is such a key component of the course. Our individual response to the material differs depending on our experiences and thus how we relate to the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course is needed because it provides the individual with a rare opportunity to feel empowered while exploring mental health. It provides a multidisciplinary approach that is so desperately needed to address mental health, using the tools of science and more mystical approaches. Often when discussing mental health different groups are convinced that their approach is the best, this course does not claim to be a magic cure, but recognises that to deal with a human issue, all aspects of humanity must be considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To learn more about our work, head to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/what-we-do&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="mental health" /><category term="education" /><summary type="html">Our education work involves working in London colleges and schools, providing mental health education and supporting young people to address challenges affecting individual and peer wellbeing. With the huge changes our world has experienced this year, we decided it was time to make our mental health education programme accessible to even more young people. So… we’re going online!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I co-designed and tested States of Mind’s new online mental health course. Here’s what I found…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/11/online-course.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I co-designed and tested States of Mind's new online mental health course. Here's what I found..." /><published>2020-11-11T17:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-11T17:57:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/11/online-course</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/11/online-course.html">**Our education work involves working in London colleges and schools, providing mental health education and supporting young people to address challenges affecting individual and peer wellbeing. With the huge changes our world has experienced this year, we decided it was time to make our mental health education programme accessible to even more young people. So... we're going online!** 

**Using our existing education model as the foundation, we've created and piloted our first online course. Uniting knowledge, theory and self reflection, it aims to increase understanding about mental health, ourselves, others, and our world.**

**Right now we're making final changes and plan to launch it fully in early 2021. Here, team member Ella shares what it was like to co-design the course, and then to work through the content as a learner.**

I am in a very unique position when it comes to discussing this course as I had the privilege of creating it with States of Mind founder Bea, and then completing it as a participant. As co-designer I was already very familiar with the course's content, yet I learnt so much from working through the content and gained a greater understanding of myself and others around me. I now apply the theories and ideas I have learned in my everyday life, and perhaps most importantly,  the insights I have gained through reflecting on the material in the handbook have greatly influenced how I relate to myself and those around me.

&gt; This course is not only helpful for those struggling with life, who may feel like the mental health system isn't supporting them enough, but also for anyone, young or old, who is searching for greater understanding of who they are and why they feel or act in the ways they do.

The course comprises five modules: Identity and Self Awareness; Body, Feelings, Mind; Relationships; Anxiety and Depression and Low mood. Each module delves into the chosen topic in detail but also contains information pertinent to all areas of life and the other modules. 

**‘Identity and Self Awareness’** is a nice starting point to gaining this greater understanding and it introduces the need to be vulnerable with oneself while completing the course. I personally noticed resistance in myself to some of the handbook exercises and therefore got some practice in compassionately responding to feelings of discomfort. This skill is essential for the course and will be learnt or built up as one progresses. It is a reminder that the moments where we usually respond with frustration or annoyance are usually the ones where kindness is needed the most.

**‘Body, Feelings, Mind’** begins an exploration into how we identify with the different aspects of our being and how this affects how we show up in the world. It contains a truly beautiful meditation that reminds me that 'I am my body but I am also more than that. I am my mind but I'm also more than that and I am my feelings but I also more than them'. This mantra reminds me of the complexity of our identity and that while these different aspects may seem at odds with one another they coexist beautifully within us. Meditations are a key part of the course and they remind me that while they can feel divisive sometimes, you are either a  &quot;yogi&quot; or you're not, meditation is a tool that can be accessible to all of us and can help to heighten the connection that we feel with all parts of our person. Working on this connection allows us to remember that we are whole without feeling a need to change or look externally.

These first two modules focus on possibly the most important relationship: our relationship with ourselves and this is then developed in the third module: **‘Relationships’**. It explores the idea that the company we keep has an affect on our well-being and that our primary relationships have long standing impacts on our mental health. It stresses the importance of authenticity in our relationships and the link between how we feel and how authentic we can be.

Self compassion is a key component of all the modules, but especially in ‘Relationships’. The self compassion meditation offers a chance to explore how compassionate we are with ourselves and how by adopting a more compassionate attitude we can support our well-being. It also offers a chance to have a truly transcendental experience, as I discovered. I had been lucky enough to engage with a few of Bea's meditations while creating the course, and love her style and this guided meditation is up there in my favourites for sure. Every person's experience is different and even the same person can have radically different experiences with a meditation depending on the context in which they engage with it but for me, while completing the course, I was able to connect with an embodied connectedness that is beyond words; I could almost feel myself unlearning old patterns! It was an odd feeling to be learning so much about myself while on my laptop but it is an experience I am very grateful for. This course provided me with an opportunity to look at the areas of my life that I am unhappy about and look for tangible ways to improve them. 

It is so incredibly important that courses like this exist because they give us chances to explore our feelings outside of a formal setting, like therapy, and do so in a way that engages not only our mind, but our soul and body too. There are opportunities to intellectually explore and opportunities to experience and feel, and in life these can feel disconnected. Completing this course reminded me that it is possible to show up using my mind, body and soul and that in the times when I inevitably cannot show up as fully as I wish too, kindness should be my immediate response. 

&gt; While helping to create it, I wanted the course to act as a reminder to young people that we have more power than we realise or are told. 

I spent [many years](https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/08/28/nhs-mental-health-young-people.html) feeling powerless when it came to how I felt, I thought that it was up to professionals to ‘treat’ me and when that did not work I spiralled into thinking that I could never experience life in a peaceful and fulfilling way. I want young people to know that most of the time our suffering is not permanent and that we can take steps to understand why we feel overwhelmed or why we may not feel anything a lot of the time. It took me a long time to detach from the thought that my ‘mental health problems’ were inherent and to instead see the beliefs I held as a result of what I had experienced as a child and teenager and how I had dealt with these experiences. There is no simple ‘cure’ for these feelings and neither is there one method that will work for everyone but, for me, a greater understanding of psychology and theories about mental health allowed me to take more responsibility for how I felt and to become discerning. As a young person, who is the ‘patient’, it can be tricky to express our opinions to mental health specialists. I struggled with the power imbalance between myself and various medical professionals for a long time, staying quiet even if I disagreed with their ideas or assessment of me. Completing this course has given me a greater feeling of confidence when it comes to working with professionals on my mental health. 

&gt; I no longer feel like I am being ‘treated’ but that it is a two way process of learning. 

As a young person I feel a lot of anxiety, both about external and internal affairs. The **‘Anxiety’** module of the course was therefore very helpful for me and it includes many really useful graphs and pictorial representations to enhance learning. I was able to address some anxiety surrounding the course, especially the handbook, in this module too. At first I rushed to fill up all the space when answering questions and only after taking a step back and asking ‘who am i performing for?’ was I able to recognise that sometimes less is more. Sometimes I wanted to write a paragraph and sometimes one word means much more to me. At the beginning I had not realised that I felt like I was under the same stress from school of needing to write a certain amount, trying to show that I understood the material and was engaged. The module’s focus on anxiety allowed me to tune into my own anxiety, sometimes prompted by the course material and sometimes inspired by its focus.

The module introduces the concept of limiting beliefs: beliefs that are rooted in fear. This was one of the first ideas that Bea and I explored together and I was very familiar with the notion by the time I came to this section. Surprisingly I was still challenged by these slides, reminding me that my growth never ends but simply changes and evolves. It was an important realisation that this course is not only useful for people who have never engaged with these concepts but also for people who are very familiar with them. Learning about theories and applying them to yourself are two very different experiences and I think it highlights the value that this course has for all no matter your experience. The ideas around changing and evolving are key to this course as it is fundamentally about looking at our beliefs and actions and questioning whether they serve or limit us. This does not mean that we denounce or label them in any way but that we recognise that we have changed and the behaviours that helped the past versions of ourselves cope may not apply to our present life. 

The final module **‘Depression and Low Mood’** is very intellectually stimulating. It introduces psychosocial theories of depression which will be foreign for many people and can radically alter the way those of us  with depression see ourselves and we see those we know who struggle with it. It introduces the idea that depression is not only an individual struggle but also one that affects all of society and is very much a political issue. Prior to meeting Bea and working with her, I had many experiences with CAMHs which I have elaborated on in [this article](https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/08/28/nhs-mental-health-young-people.html). In that article I argued that what young people need is a mental health system that values vulnerability, responsibility, truth and compassion and while we may not have that yet this course does embody these values. For me to explore such an emotionally charged topic like depression it was necessary to come from a place of acceptance and love and I felt the course supported me to do this. The calming look of the course, muted pastel colours and a rounded font, really helped here and it reminded me just how important the atmosphere is when talking about sensitive issues. This is another area where CAMHs fall short, the rooms that I have experienced are bare and often uncomfortable to be in. As individuals we cannot wait for CAMHs to transform themselves into the mental health system we so desperately need and so courses like this are key in taking some of the responsibility away from a failing system and placing it on ourselves. This can be a scary feeling and so it is important that individuals are supported while completing the course and is why facilitating sessions alongside individual completion is such a valuable thing and compliments nicely.

This module helps to reinforce in the individual just how widespread Depression is, especially in the Western world and how we as individuals must help to turn the tide. It is adversely affected by the shame we as a society seem to feel in talking about experiences of depression and by educating ourselves we can begin to remove the individual shame that we may feel about our own experience or about others’. There is a need for us to reduce inequality to help mental health and this provides a useful reminder that nothing is isolated, mental health work is about improving society as a whole and to advocate effectively that must be taken into account. We must acknowledge that experiences between different groups of people can be fundamentally different and that this must inform the way we approach talking about mental health and the language we use. The course takes this into account, avoiding definite language and keeping in mind that we cannot know someone else’s experience only make educated guesses about it. This is why the handbook is such a key component of the course. Our individual response to the material differs depending on our experiences and thus how we relate to the course. 

This course is needed because it provides the individual with a rare opportunity to feel empowered while exploring mental health. It provides a multidisciplinary approach that is so desperately needed to address mental health, using the tools of science and more mystical approaches. Often when discussing mental health different groups are convinced that their approach is the best, this course does not claim to be a magic cure, but recognises that to deal with a human issue, all aspects of humanity must be considered. 

**To learn more about our work, head to [this link](https://www.statesofmind.org/what-we-do).**</content><author><name></name></author><category term="education" /><category term="mental health" /><summary type="html">**Our education work involves working in London colleges and schools, providing mental health education and supporting young people to address challenges affecting individual and peer wellbeing. With the huge changes our world has experienced this year, we decided it was time to make our mental health education programme accessible to even more young people. So... we're going online!**</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The impact of school on young people’s mental health: a UCL doctoral student shares his findings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/04/the-impact-of-school-on-students-mental-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The impact of school on young people's mental health: a UCL doctoral student shares his findings" /><published>2020-11-04T09:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T09:19:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/04/the-impact-of-school-on-students-mental-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/04/the-impact-of-school-on-students-mental-health.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With our youth-led research project, Breaking The Silence, we’re exploring the impact of the UK’s educational system on young people’s mental health and wellbeing. Today we hear from Jaspar Khawaja, a doctoral student at the UCL Institute of Education, who has been collaborating with us in recent months to develop the research.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked about the impact of school on students’ mental health, a school student responded, “Higher stress levels, anxiety, depression, fear, isolation.” This is just one of many eye-opening responses from our recent student-led study, which gathered young peoples’ views about the impact of the education system on their mental health and wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my first year as a doctoral student at the Institute of Education, UCL, I undertook a research project in collaboration with States of Mind. I had previously worked in a secondary school with young people who had experienced trauma, and observed how the education and health services attempted to support them. Often, this involved diagnosing them with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) and prescribing medication, with less focus on trying to understand their perspectives and experiences. I also worked in a Child and Adolescent Mental Health Service (CAMHS) inpatient unit for adolescents with mental health problems. Over time I began to notice how many of the young people would be considered ‘well enough’ to leave the unit but would be readmitted to the unit after a few months as their problems worsened again. This indicated to me that something bigger must be going on in the lives of young people that is currently being missed, particularly in education and mental health services, and that the current approaches are potentially too limited or just not working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence suggests that mental health problems are on the rise for young people in the UK with depression, anxiety and suicide rates all increasing. A wealth of evidence already shows us that high stakes exams can directly negatively impact upon the mental health of young people.  One way the government has responded to the mental health issues suffered by young people is to trial the use of mental health support teams (MHSTs) in schools, the aim being to provide early intervention to children and young people with mental health issues. Doubtless, MHSTs will have a positive impact on some young people. However, evidence suggests that without consideration of prevention, these policies will do little to resolve the growing mental health crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crucial, unacknowledged question is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What impact does the education system have on the mental health and wellbeing of young people?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At States of Mind, we believe that understanding the causes of psychological distress, rather than treating their symptoms, requires a greater understanding of young people’s perspectives and allows solutions to be raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breaking-the-silence&quot;&gt;Breaking the Silence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, using a Participatory Action Research (PAR) approach , nine students at a London school analysed the themes gathered in a previous student project, which resulted in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/09/16/students-ofsted-open-letter.html&quot;&gt;letter&lt;/a&gt; being written to Ofsted. The students considered ways these themes could be further explored. In the current study, a different group of student researchers designed a two-part questionnaire to gather a wider sample of students’ views, containing both closed and open questions. The questionnaire aimed to explore students’ views on exams and mental well-being in the education system. Additionally, after it was introduced to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/education-inspection-framework&quot;&gt;Ofsted inspection handbook&lt;/a&gt;, the student researchers wanted to ask other young people how they would define “personal development”. The questionnaire was answered by 247 students at a different London school aged 16-18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-we-find&quot;&gt;What did we find?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only 12.96% of participants responded that their mental health was supported by the education system, raising massive questions about the impact of the education system on the wellbeing of young people. 38.06% disagreed with the statement, while 15.38% strongly disagreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Screenshot%202020-11-05%20at%2013.10.35.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot 2020-11-05 at 13.10.35.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also found as little as 17.41% thought exams prepare students well for life. 53.16% of students either disagreed or strongly disagreed with the statement, while 19.43% said they were not sure. This brings into question what the purpose of exams actually is, if not to prepare young people for future life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just 18.29% of students thought the education system supported the individual needs of students with the majority (59.75%) disagreeing or strongly disagreeing with the statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also reviewed the open question answers. Here, students were able to elaborate more as to their thoughts in response to the questions above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The core themes that emerged are best summarised as follows: ‘Exams cause overwhelming and unnecessary amounts of stress’ and ‘Exams are a poor measure of students ability’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students reported that the experience of school can “hugely worsen” the mental health of young people. They asserted that for some young people, aspects of the education system are the “sole reason for the deterioration” of their mental health. Reasons provided for this were the belief that high stakes examinations “dictate their future success”. For many students the “anxiety” and “stress” can become all-consuming. Many participants indicated that focus on exams meant they had no time to “do anything else” and this particularly “isolates some people who aren’t good at memorising facts but are still talented in their own right”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students also commonly expressed how “the school acts as a grade factory and all they focus on is statistics in terms of grades, attainment and awards”. The focus on attainment “creates an environment of competition” and “limits creativity in the sense that it teaches students to do things in a set way to get higher marks in exams.” Participants expressed anger that “everything seems to come back to exams rather than learning what you enjoy for the fun of it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a lack of consistency amongst answers to “What does personal development mean to you?” demonstrating the complexity of the term. A recurring answer was “growth as a person”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students discussed the importance of “developing into the person that you wish to be” and the need to “discover what you actually believe” and what “makes you different from others”. “Happiness, confidence, kindness and resilience” were viewed as key emotions and characteristics of personal development, with the opportunity to learn both “social skills and life skills” essential in producing them. Some participants also considered personal development to be “learning about issues in society”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-this-mean&quot;&gt;What does this mean?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst of course limited by sample size, this research provides some insight into why many English children repeatedly state that they are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.childrenssociety.org.uk/good-childhood&quot;&gt;unhappy with their school experiences&lt;/a&gt;. The exam system was particularly highlighted as an issue which should not be ignored by policy makers. Despite young peoples’ mental health gaining more attention in recent times the government continues to ignore the idea that the education system is contributing towards this. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://downloads.unicef.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2010/05/UNCRC_PRESS200910web.pdf?_adal_sd=www.unicef.org.uk.1602242406487&amp;amp;_adal_ca=so%3DGoogle%26me%3Dorganic%26ca%3D(not%2520set)%26co%3D(not%2520set)%26ke%3D(not%2520set).1602242406487&amp;amp;_adal_cw=1602242382854.1602242406487&amp;amp;_adal_id=38e16028-7f98-4596-8b7d-81341ed86373.1602242383.2.1602242383.1602242383.b3c3714c-a331-41a4-848e-b6604ddfd52a.1602242406487&amp;amp;_ga=2.82479382.1005391929.1602242383-1858952650.1602242383&quot;&gt;UN Convention on human rights&lt;/a&gt; explicitly states that children have the right to participate in decision-making about their lives. At States of Mind we acknowledge that educational practices have a large impact on children and young peoples’ health and wellbeing. They have the right to contribute to the policies that shape their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We are continuing to develop the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/09/16/breaking-the-silence.html&quot;&gt;Breaking The Silence&lt;/a&gt; project in collaboration with UCL Institute of Education. The next stage will see us work with a group of students to reimagine educational assessment. Stay tuned.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="education" /><category term="mental health" /><summary type="html">With our youth-led research project, Breaking The Silence, we’re exploring the impact of the UK’s educational system on young people’s mental health and wellbeing. Today we hear from Jaspar Khawaja, a doctoral student at the UCL Institute of Education, who has been collaborating with us in recent months to develop the research.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Schools are prioritising academic achievement over wellbeing and growth. Young people want to know why.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/04/academic-over-wellbeing-young-people.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Schools are prioritising academic achievement over wellbeing and growth. Young people want to know why." /><published>2020-11-04T09:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T09:18:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/04/academic-over-wellbeing-young-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/11/04/academic-over-wellbeing-young-people.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With our youth-led research project, Breaking The Silence, we’re exploring the impact of the UK’s educational system on young people’s mental health and wellbeing. Today we hear from Jaspar Khawaja, a doctoral student at the UCL Institute of Education, who has been collaborating with us in recent months to develop the research.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our previous study, student researchers produced a two-part questionnaire which was answered by 247 young people in a London college. The student respondents asserted that the education system directly contributes to the deterioration of the mental health of many young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To expand on these findings, our student researchers wanted to investigate in more depth through focus groups, thus providing a forum in which students could offer thoughts on the pressing issues in the education system and how things might be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What struck me most, during the focus groups with young people was how clearly they could explain problems relating to their educational and mental health experiences, and their capacity to suggest improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-we-do&quot;&gt;What did we do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, we used a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/09/28/young-people-education-research.html&quot;&gt;Participatory Action Research (PAR)&lt;/a&gt; approach in which student researchers, alongside State of Mind practitioners, devised the methodology and analysed the data. I conducted four online focus groups after student researchers identified relevant questions. Eleven young people from four different London schools volunteered to take part in the research, responding to adverts sent out by their colleges. Our research questions were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;- What impact do school examinations have on young people throughout their time in education?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;- What impact does the education system have on young people’s mental wellbeing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;- What does personal development mean to you during adolescence?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;- How do young people think their educational experiences could be improved?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-we-find&quot;&gt;What did we find?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thematic map to the left highlights the topics that were discussed during the focus groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Findings%201.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Findings 1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conducted a thematic analysis to analyse the core themes discussed in the focus groups. The student researchers supported the analysis and decided which quotes should be used to communicate the themes. Some of the key findings are below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theme-1-individual-differences-are-not-currently-accounted-for-in-educational-practices&quot;&gt;Theme 1: Individual differences are not currently accounted for in educational practices.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exam system was said to be “biased to certain students” and “doesn’t really cater to like different types of people”. Additionally, young people acknowledged that amongst their peers, some “can deal with stress better” but the education system can be “too much” for many young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theme-2-concerns-about-mental-health-and-wellbeing&quot;&gt;Theme 2: Concerns about mental health and wellbeing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students pointed out that “panic attacks”, “feeling depressed” and “eating disorders” were common experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Whether or not [mental health problems] are directly caused by school… it’s made worse by the education system,” commented a student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They asserted that the way mental health is discussed in schools is “outdated” and “cringy”, and a lack of support and understanding means that young people are often “acting as counsellors” for one another. Young people talked about feeling emotionally vulnerable and raised concerns that mental health problems are “normalised” amongst their peer group. They felt that this should not be the case for teenagers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theme-3-impact-of-the-education-system-on-the-formation-of-student-identity&quot;&gt;Theme 3: Impact of the education system on the formation of student identity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students reflected that personal development was closely tied to an individual’s identity, describing it as “being able to understand yourself and understanding how you cope with stress.” However, participants described “an identity crisis” amongst young people where they “think this is who I am now, I’m a student”. They talked about how they “put so much energy and so much stress and time into school”, meaning they don’t have the time to figure out who they are outside of education. Extracurricular activities were frequently discussed as being “identity forming” and as allowing students to discover their interests. But it was consistently suggested that little time exists to pursue these. This raises questions of how personal development can be brought into the curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theme-4-schools-prioritise-academic-achievement-over-mental-health-and-wellbeing&quot;&gt;Theme 4: Schools prioritise academic achievement over mental health and wellbeing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students expressed that the underlying message always seems to be, you still need to prioritise your studies above all else. They felt that the school system does not “value your mental health as much as they value your academic success”. The competitive nature of the education system was generally said to have a negative impacts as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You always end up feeling like you’re not doing enough in comparison to other people”… “If you’re not doing as well as everyone else, then you’re going to be a failure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theme-5-the-importance-of-relationships&quot;&gt;Theme 5: The importance of relationships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The young people discussed how the education system should provide them with the opportunity “to be introduced to different types of people” and learn from others. They also described the impact of “amazing teachers” who push them to be better, not just academically but “as a person.” Although this can be really positive, the students felt there needs to be increased “emphasis on a mutual connection or mutual trust between teachers and students”, and:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Teachers should be trained a little bit more on how to build a connection with their students”… “giving guidance on not just lessons but life as well”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theme-6-suggested-changes-to-the-education-system&quot;&gt;Theme 6: Suggested changes to the education system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants offered a range of improvements to the exam system, such as having “different ways of assessing like your competence and skills” involving “personal input” to develop curiosity rather than “working and learning for someone else.” They felt the removal of coursework has negatively impacted their emotional wellbeing and potential attainment. Young people strongly asserted that they need to have more space to relax and socialise because “if your mind’s preoccupied with studying… you just don’t think it’s very important to really figure out your own identity”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The young people questioned assumptions about the purpose of education system that many have come to accept:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“School doesn’t only have to be for learning… it doesn’t only have to be a space for academic achievement. I feel like it can be so many other things. Because I feel like part of developing and growing up is a lot more than just your grades”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-this-mean&quot;&gt;What does this mean?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this study young people questioned the overwhelming focus of the education system on academic achievement as a sole priority, at a cost to their wellbeing and growth as individuals. They indicated that the exam system results in unhealthy competition, student disempowerment, a lack of focus on the development of relationships and little recognition of individual diversity. In addition, they felt that skills and qualities that aren’t easily quantified are not valued in the education system, to the detriment of their personal development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research shows that young people are able to offer eloquent critique of the education system based on their experiences and have a range of thoughts on improvements. Their views must be placed at the centre of all decisions made in regards to the purpose of their education provision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We are continuing to develop the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/09/16/breaking-the-silence.html&quot;&gt;Breaking The Silence&lt;/a&gt; project in collaboration with UCL Institute of Education. The next stage will see us work with a group of students to reimagine educational assessment. Stay tuned.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="education" /><category term="mental health" /><summary type="html">With our youth-led research project, Breaking The Silence, we’re exploring the impact of the UK’s educational system on young people’s mental health and wellbeing. Today we hear from Jaspar Khawaja, a doctoral student at the UCL Institute of Education, who has been collaborating with us in recent months to develop the research.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">When it comes to developing as a person, the school system is failing us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/10/21/education-system-and-identity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When it comes to developing as a person, the school system is failing us" /><published>2020-10-21T13:43:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-21T13:43:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/10/21/education-system-and-identity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/10/21/education-system-and-identity.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today, London college student Reegan speaks out about how the education system’s focus on testing is detracting from young peoples’ ability to develop a strong sense of self.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up as young people, we are constantly exposed to environments that demand we establish a sense of who we are. Yet in educational environments, people show little interest in helping us to make sense of this process. The majority of the first eighteen years of our life is spent in the educational institutions, from primary to secondary to sixth form or college, with most people being encouraged to spend another three-eight years in university. In this time, each person is expected to discover and establish a strong sense of an independent and individual identity so that we feel confident and prepared to engage with our society in a meaningful way. We are told that committing our life to education is the best way to support our personal growth and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But if people listened to the experiences of young people, it would soon become clear that the education system is failing us. 
After removing other aspects of our identity such as ‘a sibling’, ‘relative’, or ‘a friend’, we find ourselves identified only as ‘students’. Nothing more, nothing less. We are pressured to abandon our passions and the things we love as we are forced to sacrifice our hobbies and interests, like sports, arts or reading, in order to be a ‘successful’ student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the eyes of Ofsted and educational institutions, a successful student is someone who achieves the top grades. By measuring success through grades, the education system fails to consider what true personal development means to young people. Personal development does not equate to perfect grades as they do not capture the multidimensional nature of intelligent or personal capability. Personal development can never truly be a priority when the focus is on preparing for exams. The term, ‘personal development’, as used by Ofsted, is not even given a workable definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Personal development should be our preparation for adult life, our ability to master skills such as teamwork, leadership, resilience, independence, creativity - crucial attributes that are required for later life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal development should be the ability to feel confident in the life choices we make, knowing we’ve had the support in the educational system to support ourselves once leaving it.
Yet, without clarity on what personal development means to academic institutions, we are left in a grey area of uncertainty. If no one at Ofsted cares enough to define it or explore ways of measuring whether students feel it is being achieved, young people are forced to conform to their limited and inadequate measure of exam performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department of Education has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/09/16/breaking-the-silence.html&quot;&gt;taken it upon themselves&lt;/a&gt;, without consulting young people, to focus on increasing the amount of A*-C grades rather than exploring how to support the personal development of students within education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the absence of an adequate framework for supporting students’ personal development, young people often experience education as a suffocating environment that limits our individuality and autonomy and in many cases, actively harms our sense of identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can leave students feeling lost, isolated and disengaged from the world after being released back into it. People, who were previously nothing more than students, have no purpose - what was once ‘studying to get an A*’ is now nothing, what was once ‘getting into a good college, sixth form or university’ is no longer of importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ex-students find it hard to come to terms with the idea that their A Levels or Btec or Degree will not guarantee a job, or a house, or financial stability, or, worst of all, happiness. In a society where many good qualifications should equate to happiness, and social and financial stability, when faced with the harsh reality that it may not be so, young people can feel as though we have failed, that it is a flaw within ourselves and easily fall into self-hatred and discontent - when in reality it is the failure of the education system that has not allowed young people to survive in the real world, it is the failure of the education system that has not provided skills of creativity, individuality, leadership, teamwork and more that is required in the ever changing job market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young people have limited what we believe we are capable of and have done since Year 6 SATs, to the extent that we allow the perception of ourselves and what we think others’ perceptions of us are to become toxic, leading to young people to believe that extreme levels of anxiety or stress and depression are normal. At the degree of which these anxiety, stress and depression levels are seen in young people across the nation; it comes a time to ask, “Is this a ‘snowflake’ generation, or have the demands of the job market and environment changed so much that the generation are unable to cope with the stresses they cause, and the stresses of the education system itself?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-forward&quot;&gt;Looking forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is by no means to say the education system should be abandoned. Education institutions provide knowledge and wisdom that cannot otherwise be gained and allow for a value of meritocracy, however making a change to allow more coursework and / or research (possibly in the style of an EPQ) instead of exams where students have to write assignments, allows for students to take more control in their learning and their passions - for example a list of History topics and the student has to pick and do an assignment on it, a list of Literature topics (books, poems, plays etc.) where students have to study thoroughly and complete an assignment. These small changes benefit students in allowing them to take their own interest in their learning, students find what they like and don’t like, it allows for their own creativity, individuality and identity to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students will choose subjects because they know they will have the opportunity to explore their passions and not have to sacrifice them instead. There should be a strong focus on skills the world will look for once we have left the education system, exercises that require teamwork, leadership, that help practice for interviews and conferences, skills that teach how to do taxes and about the economy, voting and banking. These small changes and adjustments mean young people will leave their educational institutions prepared, there will be less sense of confusion, loneliness and disconnect from society, young people will feel able to make life choices, knowing the education system prepared them for what it would be like once leaving it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identity is what unifies us and what makes us different. Why should we be denied the opportunity to find and explore it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As part of our youth-led project Breaking The Silence, Reegan has been working with other young people to explore the education system’s impact on students – and propose tangible changes for a better future. Read more about the ongoing project &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/journal/2020/09/16/breaking-the-silence.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="identity" /><category term="education" /><category term="youth" /><summary type="html">Today, London college student Reegan speaks out about how the education system’s focus on testing is detracting from young peoples’ ability to develop a strong sense of self.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The time for mental health awareness is over.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/10/10/the-time-for-mental-health-awareness-is-over.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The time for mental health awareness is over." /><published>2020-10-10T13:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T13:25:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/10/10/the-time-for-mental-health-awareness-is-over</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/10/10/the-time-for-mental-health-awareness-is-over.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On World Mental Health Day, our founder Bea reflects on her learning around what young people need and are capable of.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six years ago, as a young person and a trainee psychologist, I realised that we didn’t need more mental health awareness, we needed viable and sustainable ways of addressing the causes of young people’s distress. There’s a big difference between talking about change that is needed and taking action to make our demands a reality. But how do we get there? I definitely don’t have all the answers but I have some ideas and insights into how progress can be made. I’ve learned by watching, listening and working alongside young people and realising how much they are capable of when they are trusted to take part in the quest for solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mental-health-education&quot;&gt;Mental health education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve been finding ways to create spaces in education for young people to explore mental health in a different way, one where insights can be turned into action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work with them to design new ways of addressing the issues that directly affect their mental health.  I have had the privilege of bearing witness to young people sharing their inner world with myself and each other, in classrooms for 3 years now. I follow them on a journey as we commit to exploring this area of life with each other every week for 2 terms. There are many things I have learnt in those rooms that I wish people could know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The first idea I would challenge is that young people find it hard to talk about mental health, and that we need more mental health ‘awareness’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young people often tell me they find mental health awareness days patronising, repetitive and dull. They know they have difficult thoughts and emotions, they can google search what is being told to them and many already have. They want an opportunity to find answers to their problems. And yes, there can be an intense and sheepish feeling in the first session we have together but very soon I notice it transforming into what feels like a box of stories starting to open as they are given an opportunity to explore their experience more personally. Young people are extremely eloquent when speaking about their mental health and are often more open and willing to share their experiences than most adults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They share instances where they have felt judged, key times in life when something affected them deeply, sometimes seemingly insignificant events are revealed to have had a huge personal impact. They share, reflect and find meaning in their experiences, together. The young people I work with always listen to each other with a humble respect – nobody interrupts. They acknowledge each other and relate with compassion and gentleness as they begin to recognise that they are not alone in their suffering and that they can explore their experiences together. The maturity and emotional intelligence they show when discussing traumatic events is humbling and compelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t speak about mental health in the way a lot of people do. I don’t mention disorders, or chemical imbalances. I don’t speak with clinical language or psychological jargon. We talk about life and the emotional impact it can have. Sometimes I’ll teach them something I found useful, introduce them to a model through which they can reflect on their experience. The less I am an ‘expert’, the more they relax. Sometimes, I share about times I have experienced anxiety, fear of failure and hopelessness. They always seem to breathe a sigh of relief to know I feel these feelings too, that nobody is immune to the struggles of life. Often, we see psychologists as experts, as the bearers of knowledge and solutions. I find this idea extremely unhelpful when working with young people and notice the biggest shifts in their perspective when they start to realise they hold the knowledge they need within and among each other. Guiding them to find the answers, rather than presenting them with information, creates the biggest internal shifts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There’s an energy that often emerges in these spaces, it’s an energy of deep understanding and realisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes they will tell me they finally have words to describe something they have known but couldn’t put into language, or they have felt a sense of peace for the first time in months. Sometimes they are moved to tears when listening to each other’s stories. Sometimes they are exhausted from their day at school and just want to sleep. But  I have seen time and time again that with the correct space provided for them, young people demonstrate enormous courage and compassion. They learn quickly, absorbing and integrating psychological skills and knowledge faster than most adults I know. It often feels like they have been waiting to be given these spaces. They want to be there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mental-health-innovation&quot;&gt;Mental health innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Perhaps the greatest misconception that I feel compelled to challenge is that young people are less able to contribute to systems change because of their age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have incredibly creative, intuitive and fast minds. They work at a speed I sometimes find difficult to keep up with. They clearly see what the problems are and can prototype effective solutions to complex issues in two hours. Their teams function as highly efficient think tanks around young people’s mental health. I’ll give you an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, a team recognised social media was causing problems for their peers. One of the students came up with an idea. He wanted to design an app for his school to reduce social media use. The idea was brilliant: students would compete in teams, on an app, to reduce their use of the big social media platforms. In two months, he had designed and coded the entire app, found a way to measure their screen time on different platforms and produced an in-app leaderboard so teams could see who was winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It’s much harder to reduce your social media use when everyone is on it, so why not find a way to get everybody to use it less by competing to not let each other down.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had tapped into a psychological truth: we are more likely to behave pro-socially if we think people are watching, and that we are motivated to commit to our personal goals when we feel we are part of a team.  He registered the app on Android and tested it out in his college. It worked. If this was a publicly funded research project, it could have potentially cost hundreds of thousands of pounds and taken a few years to build. Give young people their voice and they will show you the solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, students across six colleges came up with more than 70 ideas like this of how to solve issues affecting their mental health. Their challenge is to focus on addressing the causes of problems, not the symptoms. We only have time for them to focus on three projects per team and that often feels like a lot due to the time limitations within schools. But they are incredibly focused, driven and reflective. Each week they think about how they can improve their idea, they iterate it, evaluate it, try again. Just like social entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s much more I could say, but one thing I am sure of is that there exists a huge amount of hope and potential for changing the landscape of mental health education in schools. I have found three ingredients to be essential to this: space, time, and reducing the power imbalance between young people and professionals. These are resources schools are lacking and need help to create, but they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; being created. Young people hold enormous power, and we must be careful not to restrict them, or misunderstand them. Because in many ways, they are leading the charge and inspiring the change we so often talk about needing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s hope to be found in many places but it requires that we lay down ideas about ‘experts’ having the solutions, and find ways to make space for the people in need to show us the way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can learn more about our work, from mental health education to youth-led research projects, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statesofmind.org/what-we-do&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and keep up to date at our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/statesofmindorg_/&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/statesofmind_20&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="mental health" /><category term="young people" /><category term="innovation" /><summary type="html">On World Mental Health Day, our founder Bea reflects on her learning around what young people need and are capable of.</summary></entry></feed>