<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-30T22:56:28+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">States of Mind</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">My experience of our mental health care system showed me what young people really need</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/08/28/nhs-mental-health-young-people.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My experience of our mental health care system showed me what young people really need" /><published>2020-08-28T09:35:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-28T09:35:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/08/28/nhs-mental-health-young-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/08/28/nhs-mental-health-young-people.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In our work, we speak with many young people about their experiences, perspectives and ideas on our society’s approach to mental health care. Today, we hear from Ella Gregory, as she shares her journey and views on what needs to change so that young people have the support to grow, learn, be well and happy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Treatment with the NHS is a minefield of complications. Not only are you likely to encounter mental health staff or doctors whose words trigger you, but you may not even qualify as ‘severe enough’ to get help, a rejection that can enable a common painful desire to compete to be the sickest. Despite this, seeing their GP is the first step in many teenagers’ journey of learning about themselves. Through this, many young people are unwillingly pushed into a mindset of ‘treating’ their ‘issues’, which not only implies that there is something wrong with them but which can quite naturally give way to feelings of anger and resentment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The idea that such patients are ill implies that mental health is simply a medical issue, rather than an ongoing process of learning and unlearning. Reorganising structures in your mind is a journey taken over the course of a lifetime with many new paths and avenues, one that can be helped by, but is not solved by, medication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragedy of such services is that they neglect a side of healing that is not medical. The NHS are there to cure and to treat and to fix, and yet most of us escape the confines of distress through introspection and by replacing old behaviours with new ones. To me, the idea that we can visit a therapist and be rid of our issues is a myth. The NHS cannot cure those of us who have been traumatised or hurt, but it can give us the resources to heal ourselves, and can support that journey for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue for me isn’t that the NHS failed to ‘fix’ me: I no longer believe that I am broken. It’s that despite using NHS services, I was not taught that my distress was a consequence of not being able to cope with my childhood or events in my life, or that I had the power to alter the way I thought about myself. I thought I was ill and sick and abnormal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ‘sickness’ label not only makes teenagers feel like they are not enough but, in my experience, also furthers their anger and feelings of despair when they may not feel better. This feeds into hostile attitudes about NHS mental health services, especially CAMHS, forming an opinion that is now commonplace and, as far as I can see, hasn’t been addressed. Why is a feeling of intense frustration and anger towards a fundamentally beneficial organisation so commonplace?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-time-for-change&quot;&gt;It’s time for change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My overwhelming feelings or periods of numbness haven’t disappeared over the years, but I am able to manage them with a lot more confidence, thanks to a form of psycho-education from my psychotherapist and the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Ella%20photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ella photo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thanks to my experiences, I know that the NHS do not lack the resources to help young people – but they must change the way they help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One fundamental issue is that NHS services are privy to cuts and politics, and private help is a privilege that many cannot access. With a recognition that the NHS will never be able to commit fully as understanding mental health is not their sole mission, we as patients can have more realistic expectations, and NHS professionals can focus on giving us the skills we need to live a fulfilled life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHS’ diagnostic model is an issue for many people: binding them to the limits of their diagnosis, it can cause people to dismiss symptoms that don’t fit in with the criteria, or self diagnose in an effort to explain such symptoms. Meanwhile, other avenues and tools such as the Power Threat Meaning Framework, are not presented to patients, leaving them unexposed to ways of thinking that could inspire a hope and zeal for life. There are many ways to combat our behaviours and help ourselves, and yet when receiving treatment from the NHS, it feels like so many avenues are shut off to you. Not only do the staff not seem to know about them but there doesn’t seem to be a willingness to learn about different paths we can take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Additionally, resources do not inspire connection – strange, when many point to a lack of connection as the nub of why as a society we are so distressed and lonely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trained mental health professionals seem to have no idea about how to help us connect other than seeing our friends. Meditation can be a powerful tool to connect us but using apps on our own in our rooms is not the only way to do it. We can connect online through communities, built by influencers like Yoga with Adriene, Fleur deliss and David Nitchern; people who not only guide us with words of wisdom, but also smile, speak with emotion and offer the chance to engage with members of the community they have built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taking-responsibility&quot;&gt;Taking responsibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accepting another person’s help with such an intimate and terrifying journey requires trust. We must not only trust in the method and the practitioner but in ourselves. As patients we have a certain amount of responsibility to keep trying, to be honest with ourselves and others, to trust our instincts, to defend our beliefs and to educate others when they hurt us. This duty extends also to medical professionals and therapists. Not only are they not exempt in making mistakes, but there is an often unspoken-about power imbalance that is especially prevalent with young people. When challenging someone with a university degree over their approach or words, it is easy to give up because they are more experienced, but we owe it to ourselves and to those who will use these services in the future to challenge comments that are triggering and hurtful, to be honest when we are scared. In this way, we can help improve the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NHS encourages self-awareness, but does not share tools to learn it. So the responsibility falls on those of us who are suffering to recognise the limitations and flaws in the service, realise the power we have to change and empower ourselves, look for growth in times when you feel that the system fails you, and extract resilience and self-responsibility from these experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing ideas that have been ingrained in us is an arduous, life-long journey. It involves  reading, learning, unlearning, listening, trying, failing, practicing and talking and it is something we cannot rely wholly on the NHS for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yes, the NHS can fail to meet our needs. But as young people, we cannot use this as an excuse not to do the work ourselves and to do this the NHS must make it clear that the responsibility is on the young person to continue their healing journey and recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;truth-and-compassion&quot;&gt;Truth and compassion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often fear that without system wide change, the NHS will continue to fail young people and rely on outdated methods, but there is still potential for small changes that can have huge results. Not only do paediatricians, GPs and other non mental health specific professionals need to learn more about what it’s like to feel so distressed and lost at a young age but they must also be taught to communicate better. They must actively engage in programmes (for example, peer to peer counselling services like Talk 4 Health) in which they can learn how to respond to someone who may feel utterly alone in their struggle and hopefully build a level of self awareness that can help to undo the anger felt by many. NHS staff must be honest about their own shortcomings and be honest with their patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a young person, I can provide my perspective: condescending tones and conversations with family members that did not include me only served to further complicate and confuse things.
Maybe at the time we won’t be able to deal with what you tell us, but I have found it much more helpful to hear truths than to be mollycoddled. If the fear is around the patient angrily responding, then instead of not sharing these truths, CAMHS should look into creating a safe space to destress after a session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I do not believe that it is possible to treat someone if you are assuming their hostility. As such, staff within mental health systems and in any medical profession need to set a good example by practicing love and compassion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vulnerability is a tool that I see as key to enjoying life and being able to be vulnerable is a skill that many have to learn. We are surrounded by messages that are anti-vulnerability and the NHS should be a haven from these. Vulnerability must be reciprocated, we all have a duty to be as honest as we can, whether we are the patient or the provider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young people are angry, but under that hostility is a soul longing to be loved and understood. Together we can work to restore our voices and feel authentic, as long as we have a mental health system that values honesty and responsibility.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side photo: Ella Gregory, 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="mental health" /><category term="care" /><category term="young people" /><summary type="html">In our work, we speak with many young people about their experiences, perspectives and ideas on our society’s approach to mental health care. Today, we hear from Ella Gregory, as she shares her journey and views on what needs to change so that young people have the support to grow, learn, be well and happy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to States of mind</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/23/welcome-to-states-of-mind.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to States of mind" /><published>2020-05-23T12:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-23T12:12:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/23/welcome-to-states-of-mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/23/welcome-to-states-of-mind.html">&lt;p&gt;Hi, we’re States of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re combining education and social action to give mental health a new meaning – one founded in empowerment and connection, rather than confusion and separateness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve designed a mental health education model that helps young people develop self understanding, emotional intelligence and leadership skills, while creating solutions to the issues causing distress amongst their peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we also design research projects that explore how our society can better support the emotional and mental wellbeing of young people, today and in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-are-we-here&quot;&gt;Why are we here?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing numbers of young people in the UK are seeking help for their mental health, but many aren’t getting the support they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the NHS unable to meet the rising demand, we believe it’s time for a new approach, one that is co-created with young people outside of clinical settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-we-doing&quot;&gt;What are we doing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;→ Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody experiences emotional distress as a young person, but without the right information and tools, it can be hard to know how to deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why we need to support young people to develop the skills, confidence, and knowledge to look after their mental health, and seek help when they need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We run trauma-informed mental health education programs in schools, giving young people the tools to explore their minds and emotions in a safe and familiar environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our group learning model fosters an understanding that challenging experiences are part of life for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through practical exercises in self awareness and reflection, students learn how we can move through times of suffering with compassion, connection, and hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;→ Social action and research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mental health concerns are often spoken about as isolated and individual problems, but we believe they are inseparable from the environments we grow up in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through social action and research, we work to understand and repair the systemic issues that contribute to young people’s distress. This comes to life in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our education program, which is designed around project based learning. Students identify key issues in their school and community that are affecting the wellbeing of their peers, and then design and lead a social impact initiative to address the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We design research projects to enable young people’s voices inspire new ways of thinking about mental health, and inform the way our society supports wellbeing. Working with young people and psychologists, we uncover issues within our social and education structures, and explore different approaches that may better support young people’s needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can learn more about our current research project with UCL, ‘Breaking The Silence’, here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-are-we-different&quot;&gt;How are we different?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our mission is driven by a desire to co-create a future for mental health that is built from a foundation of autonomy, choice and freedom of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We envision a world where it’s natural to talk about and care for our emotional and mental wellbeing. Where times of suffering don’t disconnect us, but help us align with who we are, acknowledge our needs, and make sense of our lives, together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make sure this future works for young people, we need to leverage their voices, experiences, and ideas as a driving force for meaningful change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is at the heart of our work, and we’re so excited to share it with you as it unfolds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-can-i-get-involved&quot;&gt;How can I get involved?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Student? Educator? Parent? If you like the sound of our program and would like to bring it to your school, contact us here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also bringing together people who share our values, to collaborate on projects that can enhance society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to work with us? Great – we’ve got a big mission, and we need talented, creative, passionate people to help us realise it. We’d love to hear from you, so reach out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also just love hearing different people’s experiences and ideas. Get in touch if you have something you’d like to share or chat about with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re working towards making our education program accessible online. Watch this space.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="States of mind" /><summary type="html">Hi, we’re States of mind.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The power of self awareness, and how to cultivate it</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/22/cultivating-self-awareness.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The power of self awareness, and how to cultivate it" /><published>2020-05-22T20:41:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T20:41:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/22/cultivating-self-awareness</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/22/cultivating-self-awareness.html">&lt;p&gt;According to the poet William Meredith, the worst thing that can happen in the life of a man is that “he did not pay attention”. In the busyness of modern life, rarely are we provided with safe spaces to step back and consciously reflect on our mental and emotional wellbeing. Without this ability to reflect and process the meaning in our everyday life and personal experience, we can easily become caught up in unhealthy unconscious behaviour and feel unfulfilled with how things are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest gifts of humankind is having the possibility to constantly reinvent yourself and to endlessly explore and learn about this collective human experience. As we develop a practice of self awareness, we can experience a richer life, we can allow deep healing and expand ourselves  by opening up space within us to establish meaning and foster change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-self-awareness&quot;&gt;What is self awareness?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self awareness is a human faculty that enables us to become observers of our own life journey. It allows us to witness – without judgement – our mental, emotional and physical states. Through self awareness, we can make sense of and process our human experience with the powerful gift of conscious attention. By developing this natural aptitude, we can learn to regulate the quality of our reality and access an empowering sense of freedom and choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The insights we gain through self awareness can help to shape the life we want and motivate us to become the person we want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when we can connect to our authenticity, we gain clarity around the changes we want to make to support ourselves and have more meaningful relationships. Without self awareness, we can become unconscious to our behaviours, repress our feelings and intuitions and often depart from living in alignment with our true values and best interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man is a social animal, as defined by Aristotle, and although our learning process is individual, there can also be value in others’ perception, essential to form a fuller sense of self. According to a study conducted by organisational therapist, researcher and New York Times bestselling author Tasha Eurich, there are two types of self awareness:
internal self awareness (how clearly we see ourselves, our own values, our own thought process, passions, aspirations, emotions and behaviours)
external self awareness (how other people view us and our place in the world).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Western societies, some of the most popular methods used to develop self awareness are creative processes, physical exercise, meditation, journaling and therapy. The list goes on but there’s no right way to ‘pay attention’ or be ‘self aware’ – your own journey is unique to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At States of Mind, we’re passionate about the benefits of self awareness, so we create safe spaces for young people to learn about and develop it for themselves.The teenage and young adult years are an ideal time to explore and nurture self awareness, allowing us to grow in a direction of our choice. We believe that by giving more people the opportunity to develop self awareness from a young age, they can learn to manage difficult experiences with more confidence and live significantly happier, healthier lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Self%20awareness%20(Photo%20by%20Marwane%20Pallas).jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Self awareness (Photo by Marwane Pallas).jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cultivating-self-awareness-our-top-5-tips&quot;&gt;Cultivating self awareness: Our top 5 tips&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-focus-on-the-what-and-not-the-why&quot;&gt;1. Focus on the WHAT and not the WHY&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is essential to get started and to avoid unhealthy patterns and negative self talk. As you start reflecting on your journey so far and where you want to take it, you might feel moments of judgement towards yourself and the world around you. Observe, but don’t judge and focus on what it is you see instead of why it is as you see it. Be aware of rumination, which is a form of internal awareness linked to anxiety and depression where you focus on negative and painful stories around your past and present self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-take-the-time&quot;&gt;2. Take the time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self awareness can become a habit that we value and enjoy. Most of us already have moments of self awareness throughout our days when we have a chat (to another person, or with ourselves) about our mental state, when take a big deep breath, or when we write in our journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of developing self awareness becomes more powerful and sustainable when we set the time aside and feel committed to ourselves. Whether it’s a set time with a friend or a psychologist, a dedicated time to exercise or write, a day to take yourself on a date and reflect on your journey so far; set the time aside to develop self awareness and make it one of your healthy priorities. You may think that you have more important things to do, however look at it as a time investment that will eventually come back to you with a better life quality and feeling of authenticity in being yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-create-a-safe-space&quot;&gt;3. Create a safe space&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often hear the phrase “safe space” or “create a space” and we may wonder, “What makes a space safe?” A safe space can be a physical space (a sanctuary of your own, a bedroom, an altar, a garden, a café you love, a journal) and also a mental space (a space inside yourself that you can find by closing your eyes, through meditation, relaxation, breathing techniques – somewhere you feel safe to hear your inner voice). Ideally, you should try to find both a physical sanctuary and a mental space. You can find some guidance in how to develop a self reflective practice with our next article in the journal. This is a guided method to get started on your self reflective practice that will lead you to your safe space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-ask-questions&quot;&gt;4. Ask questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get into the habit of checking in with yourself. Ask yourself a few times a day “How am I feeling right now?” Just sit with the question for a few moments, meditate on it, or write your immediate thoughts in a journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also be helpful to get external insight from those who know you. Identify some things about yourself that you would like more clarity on, and ask your friends, family members, psychologist, teachers their thoughts. It may seem counterintuitive to look to others for insight about yourself, but it can help to create a well-rounded perspective of yourself. But take a moment to imagine your awareness is a room. Naturally, you only have your own perception of this room, and the more you get another perspective, the more you’ll know it from all the different angles. There is no right or better angle, just a greater understanding of your own story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-cultivate-imagination-and-empathy&quot;&gt;5. Cultivate imagination and empathy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self awareness allows you to become the observer of your thought process, of your mind, of your body and of the world around you. In short, it can help bring a different sense of consciousness and a greater attention to things in your life. But developing it takes time and effort, and so you want to have as many tools as possible to help you on this journey. Here are two of the key ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imagination: Cultivate your imagination through creative practice, conversation with strangers, travelling and trying out new things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Empathy: Self awareness enables us to live with greater compassion for ourselves and others. By recognising and bringing attention to the parts of ourselves that we sometimes judge, ignore or deny, we can build a stronger relationship with ourselves, connect more fully in our relationships and the things we do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, we all share a collective human experience. Self awareness is a gift that can expand our understanding of what it means to be human, and to be on this wild ride called life, together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Learn more about how our programmes help to foster self awareness and emotional intelligence &lt;a href=&quot;http://statesofmind.org/what-we-do&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Tascha Eurich, “What Self-Awareness Really Is (and How to Cultivate It)”, Harvard Business Review, 2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="self awareness" /><summary type="html">According to the poet William Meredith, the worst thing that can happen in the life of a man is that “he did not pay attention”. In the busyness of modern life, rarely are we provided with safe spaces to step back and consciously reflect on our mental and emotional wellbeing. Without this ability to reflect and process the meaning in our everyday life and personal experience, we can easily become caught up in unhealthy unconscious behaviour and feel unfulfilled with how things are.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to start a reflective journaling practice: our simple tips</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/22/reflective-journaling-practice.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to start a reflective journaling practice: our simple tips" /><published>2020-05-22T20:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T20:38:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/22/reflective-journaling-practice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/22/reflective-journaling-practice.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I never travel without my diary. One should always have something sensational to read in the train.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oscar Wilde was right. A diary recalls one’s sensation from the past, present, and future, so it follows that it would always be a sensational read. Wilde humours his audience by hinting that his life was always more interesting than any character from a novel, and considering his biography and fantastic work of art, he was probably right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not all future Oscar Wildes and we may not have the ambition to write an impressive body of work in theatre, poetry and literature, but I’ll take a risk in suggesting that we may all share the ambition to grow and improve as human beings in our lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the art of self-reflection comes in. Writing a self-reflective journal is about being an active witness of your own experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By taking a closer look at yourself, you can find clarity on who you were, who you are and who you wish to become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all encounter countless teachers in our life. Our first teachers are our parents, then our primary school teachers, our friends, our first boyfriends or girlfriends and the list goes on. But ultimately, the main teacher who remains with us our entire life is ourselves. By developing the habit of reflecting on and learning through our own experience, we become simultaneously the teacher and the student to our own self. With time and practice we can become our most reliable teacher. Once we learn to trust our instinct, we can reflect and analyse our experience and dare to share our dreams with ourselves and the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, a reflective practice is the habit of thinking and reflecting on what you do and who you are, and journaling can be an effective approach. There is no right or wrong way to write a journal, but below are some simple tips to help you get started:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-make-it-a-habit&quot;&gt;1. Make it a habit&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether it is everyday or every week, the regularity of your practice will help you create a safe space for your mind which can help you learn to trust yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-dont-worry-just-write&quot;&gt;2. Don’t worry, just write&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try writing without an agenda, structure, or plan. Practice automatic writing, just letting whatever’s on your mind flow onto the page. Though you may have no idea what you’re writing, your subconscious will absorb the content and you may find that later on you come to a new realisation about yourself or something in your life. Let the process be intuitive: if you want to write the same sentence 10 times, do it; if you want to doodle for 10 minutes, do it. Trust your mind to take you where you need to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-write-to-someone-else&quot;&gt;3. Write to someone else&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write as if you are addressing your inner child, your future self, or perhaps your best friend or a stranger. This can help make it easier to share information about your feelings and your deepest thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-ask-questions&quot;&gt;4. Ask questions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to know an answer on a decision you should make or whether something would be good for you to do? Write the question down, then leave it for a day or a week. When you return to it, try to answer with the first thing that comes to your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-focus-on-the-details&quot;&gt;5. Focus on the details&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are often told not to focus too much on details, but journaling is an amazing opportunity to do exactly that. Write to explore your experience in depth and insist on anything that caught your attention. Start with the five senses: what did you see, feel, smell, taste or hear?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;6-read-and-reflect&quot;&gt;6. Read and reflect&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid reading your words as you write them: choose a separate time to read your entries. At the end of your journaling session, or once a month, take the time to read what you wrote without judgment and note the evolution of your thoughts and emotions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="self awareness" /><category term="journalling" /><summary type="html">“I never travel without my diary. One should always have something sensational to read in the train.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting to know our youth-led research project, Breaking the silence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/22/breaking-the-silence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting to know our youth-led research project, Breaking the silence" /><published>2020-05-22T20:32:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T20:32:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/22/breaking-the-silence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/22/breaking-the-silence.html">&lt;p&gt;Breaking the Silence is a youth-led research project exploring young people’s views on how aspects of the UK education system are having an impact on their mental health, identity and personal development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;States of Mind views mental health concerns in the context of young people’s lives and seeks to identify with young people, the causes of their distress. The purpose of this project was to provide young people with the opportunity to speak about their experiences in education and to use their voices to help inform at a policy level, new ways in which schools can create more psychologically healthy environments for students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project was initiated in response to Ofsted’s consultation on their new Inspection Framework in January 2019. Ofsted Inspections have a significant influence on young people’s experience of education as it drives every school’s focus on academic attainment and exam performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the period of the consultation, 80 students have shared their views around their experience in education, exploring Ofsted’s influence on the culture of schools and the subsequent impact this has on student’s mental health and identity.The results expose a complex account of how the UK education system, under Ofsted’s current framework, is contributing to a decline in the mental health of students.  The working group have revealed an account, that provides a new context for understanding a factor contributing to the rising levels of mental health concerns experienced by young people. Student’s have summarised their findings in an open letter to Amanda Speilman, calling for their voices and experiences to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sharing from Julia, student working group member:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have been doing work experience with States of Mind for 10 weeks and I have learned a lot more not only about mental health but also how it fits in our society today.  States of Mind has allowed me to be able to see the bigger picture and feel like, for once, my opinion and the voices of other young people have been listened to and that they actually matter. I enjoyed every week and every activity that we did and I genuinely feel like all of it has a purpose and that it should become a much bigger deal and acknowledged by more people. I would recommend States of Mind to anyone who cares about the current system and who wants to learn more not just about the world but about themselves. The whole experience has been enjoyable and I have learnt skills that I will take with me for life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s in the interest of parents, employers and society as a whole to advocate for an education system that enables young people to flourish as individuals, with unique skill sets, ambitions and confidence in speaking their views critically and truthfully with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But often, young people’s experience of education feels limiting, minimising their sense of choice, personal identity and unique personal interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research project allowed young people to lead the conversation around their experience in education and explore the issues that most mattered to them. As the primary stakeholders of education, their voices are key to understanding the issues and proposing reforms that can enable a more engaging and fulfilling experience of learning and developing within school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effects of high stakes testing should not be underestimated. Students reported often feeling shamed by teachers and their families if they were unable to meet the academic requirements expected of them.  Meanwhile students are aware that non- academic routes will often suit their needs better and can even place them ahead of their peers in terms of access to employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students feel that often, the role of teachers seems to be to teach to the test, rather than fostering supportive relationships that allow them to explore and uncover their personal ambitions and interests. Students recognise the stress placed on teachers,  which reduces their sense of being able to ask for help, for fear that the mindset they will receive is that they are not ‘good students’. Schools, with increasing pressure to obtain academic results from their students, often respond to mental health problems in a reactive way- responding to students in crisis, feeling unable to offer the care and support that is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings from the young people’s work so far illustrate how young people want to be seen as individuals, with individual needs and unique ambitions. Ofsted inspections focus school’s targets on Academic performance, rather than their ability to provide a holistic and student focused culture of general wellbeing and self determination. There is a stigma around non academic pathways and alternative routes to employment which frames less academic students as having ‘failed ‘ the ‘ true test of intelligence’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The research the student’s have initiated continues to develop with States of Mind recently collaborating with UCL to develop the research base.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listen to our podcast episode on the Breaking the Silence project, below.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://anchor.fm/bea-herbert/embed/episodes/Breaking-The-Silence--Young-peoples-views-on-Education-and-Identity-eeb7ej&quot; height=&quot;102px&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="research" /><category term="breaking the silence" /><summary type="html">Breaking the Silence is a youth-led research project exploring young people’s views on how aspects of the UK education system are having an impact on their mental health, identity and personal development.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meet Neeraja: “We have started a chain of people talking about mental health”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/21/meet-neeraja-wellbeing-ambassador.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meet Neeraja: &quot;We have started a chain of people talking about mental health&quot;" /><published>2020-05-21T21:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-21T21:40:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/21/meet-neeraja-wellbeing-ambassador</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/21/meet-neeraja-wellbeing-ambassador.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the best things about our work is collaborating with inspiring young people from all over London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our Wellbeing Ambassadors Programme, we teach secondary school and college age students about mental health and emotional intelligence, provide a space for them to explore their mind, behaviour and identity, and hear their ideas for how their learning environment could be a happier, healthier place. Then we help turn those ideas into reality, as students use what they’ve learned to design and run an initiative to improve wellbeing at their school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first part of our new series of interviews with students in the programme, we speak with Neeraja, who was part of the first cohort in Newham Borough. As project manager for the team, she oversaw the development of not one but two new wellbeing initiatives for her college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Neeraja’s team designed and co-facilitated peer talking groups for wellbeing which were run as lunchtime drop in sessions and in tutorials, as well as launching the Nameless Book, an opportunity for students across her college to submit stories about what they learned from overcoming challenging experiences in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sat down together to hear her thoughts on the experience and find out how the projects went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From starting the wellbeing ambassadors programme, to the end, what changes have you noticed in yourself?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before the programme started, I was pretty open about discussing mental health and making other people aware of it. But I’ve realised that I’ve gained more confidence in talking about it since becoming a wellbeing ambassador. After the training, I felt like I had more authority to talk about [mental health], I felt as if I was more aware and that I could actually talk about it with confidence. It also really helped me build my leadership, communication and active listening skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And is that what you expected when you started?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly didn’t expect anything when I came into it, I knew that it was something that I was passionate about so I felt like if I could do anything to help that would be great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What impact has the experience had on your understanding of mental health?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme definitely helped improve my understanding of mental health, and helped me see mental health with a different perspective. All I had known about mental health was through my education as I had done Psychology for GCSE’s, so my knowledge was more educational rather than practical. So when I started the programme I started to understand how mental health is [a part of real life], not just how it is written down in books or how it is described in medical terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also helped me develop a perception of it, I could see how different people in college and other wellbeing ambassadors viewed mental health and what their opinions were, not just my own. It was really a great experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has talking about mental health been useful for you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes it has, it has been very useful, personally and also for everyone else. I think we have definitely created an impact in college because we have started a chain of people talking about mental health, whereas beforehand it wasn’t nearly as big a focus as it should have been. Even though it is a tiny change, we have changed the way people think about mental health at our college. I really think we have made a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What potential do you see the programme having?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely see the programme improving and growing over the next few years, and more people joining. I would like to see more wellbeing ambassadors, male and female, and would like to see the changes that we started continued. I’m really looking forward to [our project’s] book and the group support sessions. They have been very successful which is really great and we have had pretty positive reviews from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Could you tell me a bit about the group support session that you ran and what that was like for you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well at the start there was this awkwardness and nobody knew how to start talking, but once people started talking everyone was really open. We were talking about the different fears we have, like the fears around safeguarding, how there have been knife attacks. We talked about some of the main issues, like how there has been crime in Newham and everything and we started to hear, it wasn’t just us but so many other people were impacted by it on a more personal level actually. Even the tutors, there were two tutors with us, even they had similar experiences to us and we started to see that the adults who we see as different to us are not as different as we think. They basically have the same experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some students who still had trouble opening up completely but I think that if they keep coming to the support sessions it would actually be a really nice space for them. We also found out that other students in college feel alone and lonely, as if they have no friends there, and for them we realised it would be such a great opportunity, because it’s like a new friendship group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was it like to co-facilitate the group?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start we wanted to make people feel safe with us, because we didn’t want them to feel like we were in charge of them or like we were conducting an interview or something. So we started talking about our own experiences. Tisha and I started sharing our own experiences and how we were feeling and they started to realise it wasn’t us against them, more like ‘we are all in this together’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was good, it was fun. I mean, there were times when we completely ran out of ideas but it always somehow came naturally to us, like we would get a bit stuck and unsure of what to talk about next but then somebody else would start talking and we would realise, ‘OK wait, we don’t need to do anything, it will take care of itself’, it was so organic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And what’s great is you now have those skills and you can take them to other places. If you wanted to take that to university, you could.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah it would be great if we could continue with it somehow. Tisha and I are both going to university and so we could each take it with us. It would be great, like a chain that we started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you think this approach to raising awareness about mental health could impact schools and other educational settings?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that the approach we took is more friendly – instead of a psychologist and the patient dynamic, it’s more like two people having a conversation. I think this helps because in school I’ve noticed that when people mention mental health, it’s more like you’re crazy, that’s the way that they see it. But I think our approach would raise the awareness that is necessary to eradicate those kinds of perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think it can help the teacher student relationship immensely, in the way that we deal with mental health. I think teachers should be able to deal with it in the way we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And what you were saying about the support groups and the tutors being there, it’s as if you have already started to change those relationships?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, because through some of the talks, we realised that the tutors also go through problems like us and they are not completely strangers to this. You know, there’s this whole idea that teachers won’t understand what we are going through. I think projects like this would take away that idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it mean for your school to have brought the programme in this year?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it should have been brought out earlier to be honest. If it had been brought out last year I definitely would have been more involved and I’m kind of sad that I won’t be getting another year. It is such a great programme and I think it will really help change a lot of student’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Community" /><summary type="html">One of the best things about our work is collaborating with inspiring young people from all over London.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I learned that vulnerability isn’t a weakness, it’s a strength</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/20/vulnerability-isnt-a-weakness-its-a-strength.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I learned that vulnerability isn’t a weakness, it’s a strength" /><published>2020-05-20T11:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-20T11:38:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/20/vulnerability-isnt-a-weakness-its-a-strength</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/2020/05/20/vulnerability-isnt-a-weakness-its-a-strength.html">&lt;p&gt;I used to assume that every action we took, every word we spoke and every time we felt an instant connection towards someone, there would always be a consequence. This sense of paranoia and lack of trust in anyone helped to build a mental link between “vulnerable” and “not capable of doing something substantial for people who were important to me.” I assumed that this was inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But last year, I spoke with a group of young people who talked about vulnerability being the pinpoint explanation for someone struggling with their mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I thought about my environment at school, and how vulnerability is seen as a weak attribute there. This means it’s difficult for male students to express their own emotions because they don’t want others to see them as vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, I’ve learned how important it is to have a connection with other people. According to Brené Brown, connection brings meaning and purpose to our lives. People who live in shame and fear are ultimately afraid of being disconnected with people around them, which leads them to ask, ‘Am I worthy of connection?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By avoiding showing others your imperfections or flaws, you can also avoid feelings of vulnerability. Maybe this is why men can feel forced to hide their shame – as a way to avoid vulnerability in certain circumstances. But to create a connection with another person, you need to open with each other, embrace your flaws, and be willing to share them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to enhance our connection with others, we need to seek out and foster courage, compassion and confidence – the kind that inspires everyone. I feel that being vulnerable can be perceived as a negative concept, but it’s also very positive. Being vulnerable allows us to relate to one another, because we all have imperfections in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In our society, we often expect males to be powerful, strong and not ‘to cry’ in the most tragic times. But these are outdated societal norms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We in the 21st century have so much freedom. Women are gaining more rights and security, the gender pay gap is getting smaller and the LGBTQ+IA community is becoming freer than ever. These progressions have come from actions people have taken to transform society for the better. So why is it that we still assume that men shouldn’t show emotion or vulnerability?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue affects everyone, not only men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s time to understand that it’s okay to be vulnerable, because vulnerability connects us to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Find out more about our Wellbeing Ambassadors Programme &lt;a href=&quot;http://statesofmind.org/what-we-do&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="vulnerability" /><category term="connection" /><summary type="html">I used to assume that every action we took, every word we spoke and every time we felt an instant connection towards someone, there would always be a consequence. This sense of paranoia and lack of trust in anyone helped to build a mental link between “vulnerable” and “not capable of doing something substantial for people who were important to me.” I assumed that this was inevitable.</summary></entry></feed>